appreciate all right hello welcome to
the active inference institute's te
textbook group uh this is cohort 8 we
are still in part one of the active
inference textbook looking at chapter 3
we know from before that we saw the
introduction to the active inference
textbook and following that was chapter
two starting from the so-called low road
to active inference as the authors have
provided us not one but two paths at
arriving at active inference the low
road started with basis theorem uh which
is a classic uh formula for uh
essentially updating one's beliefs in
the sense of we already start with some
prior beliefs we then encounter some new
evidence or
observations and then through
relating uh our beliefs with
observations we then can engage in what
we would call inference and just carry
out basis theorem in order to arrive at
a new belief or a posterior belief so
from there we can start to imagine
entire generative models uh that have um
that essentially organisms whether they
be agents or however we want to conceive
of them but some kind of generally
autonomous or or distinguishable thing
uh can have a generative model whereby
it carries out bar basis theorem in
varieties of ways including in very
important uh uh behaviors that relate to
adaptation um or otherwise such as
gaining information about one's
environment in order to update one's
beliefs uh order to better uh uh
navigate that environment and then we
had Notions of predictive coding we had
planning as inference perception as
inference um perception in one sense can
just be
viewed this is me putting it in
caricature almost like a likelihood
Matrix in the sense of we have
observations and as long as we have some
mapping uh between those observations
and hidden States
we can arrive at updating our beliefs
and this is more or less the notion of
perception as held not just an active
inference but a variety of theories and
cognitive science um again active
inference is not necessarily Reinventing
the wheel instead it is a normative
framework that draws from a variety of
fields in order to construct what is an
attempt at a much broader coherent meat
framework as as opposed to perhaps some
of the more disperate theories that
currently exist um and so then we also
have planning as inference in the basian
brain now we'll be starting from the
high road to active inference starting
with the free energy principle now what
is the free energy principle and why do
we care about it and why does it have a
nearly M magisterial sound about it
whenever we hear it out of context well
um with chapter 3 we start with this
idea that uh as the authors claim uh
active inference starts from first
principles in statistical physics and
the central imperative that organisms
must maintain their
existence so uh that is they must avoid
surprising States and then introduces
from there in the chapter the
minimization of free energy as a
computation tractable solution to this
problem so it's not simply that the free
energy principle is being stated um cely
as a a kind of mechanical logical
necessity it's actually in the service
of something whenever we view it from
the standpoint or or respective to uh
organisms or or agents within their
environment that includes looking at
concepts of s self-organization of those
agents um how they minimize their
surprisal to remain within so-called
preferred States what might be likened
to the notion of homeostasis we have the
idea of a marov blanket um which we may
have witnessed before in this um part of
the book but it is laid out much more
clearly for us in this chapter over and
above the other chapters um this is a
notion that is very much worth getting
familiar with um there are of course
debates here around them uh what a
Markov blanket is what it should entail
um and there is also an important
distinction between the marov blanket as
defined by uh uh probability and causal
inference theorist Judea Pearl uh as
opposed to how this idea is employed in
active inference um but nonetheless
there are very strong uh sort of
similarities between the two concepts
and I would like to spend just a moment
talking about Markov blankets just
because they're so essential um to
active inference and not just active
inference but any kind of of of
computational modeling right um one
quick way of saying uh getting at the
idea of a marov blanket is how do we
Define a thing and and it's initially
seems like a silly or strange question
but it becomes really important whenever
you want to engage in computational
modeling for example if you're going to
model the behavioral of a population of
of neurons in some particular area or
region of the brain you have to be able
to figure out what are the neurons what
are their boundaries and what is not the
neuron and so sometimes I've used this
this phrasing that I borrowed from
another theorist Mark SS who is a neuros
psychoanalyst who's done a lot of work
with with Carl friston in active
inference in the past where he he says
there's the system or system of interest
such as the organism and then there's
the not system right we have to figure
out what the the organism is not in
order to understand it in its
environment so the the environment is
another word for the not system in this
case and so with a marov blanket this uh
the the the author's quote an important
precondition for any adaptive system is
that it must enjoy some separation and
autonomy from the environment without
which it would simply dissipate dissolve
and thereby succumb to environmental
Dynamics and so unquote it is through
surprise minimization that a system or
organism or agent maintains this
separation from its environment so we
can see um for example in box
3.1 there is a somewhat clearer
understanding supplied to us about what
a marov blanket is but essentially if we
can identify something like blanket
States within a
system then we can start to figure out
how here they use me which could for
example represent the internal states of
the agent versus X which might be a kind
of true state of the environment by
being able to define the blanket States
we can begin to separate them out that
brings us to figure 3.1 and so uh kind
of classically in active inference the
way the phrasing is that we have the
internal States over here again defined
by mu of the organism and then we have
the external states with X but between
them we have active States and sensory
States these
both it can be slightly confusing the
way they they've placed blanket States
down here but it's actually the active
States and sensory states are both uh
considered to be blanket States between
and which essentially separate the
external and internal States and so they
phrase it as um a blanket for a variable
can be identified by taking into account
the variables parent variables which it
depends on the variables child variables
which depend on it and in some cases the
other parent variables of its children
variables what what is this about about
parent and children variables for for
those of us who are not uh fully attuned
to sort of the the the statistical
terminology here well we have
let's say we're looking at the internal
states of the organism well what do they
depend upon if we look at the arrows
here we see the sensory States the
sensory states are being fed into the
internal States What's Happening Here is
perception the agent receives through
its sensorium sensory States or
observations right so it's kind of
inheriting in
a I want to be clear that inheriting is
being used Loosely here but it's kind of
inheriting aspects of the sensory States
right it's taking them in and relating
them such that through its internal
mapping or likelihood Matrix is one way
of phrasing it it can then
infer uh its internal States for example
uh sensory I notice my stomach is
growling internal States in meaning
beliefs I now believe oh I must be
hungry my if my stomach is growling I
must be
hungry probability of hunger conditional
on on observation here in a matrix might
be incredibly high and so it leads me
quickly to make that inference from
there I could engage in let's say some
kind of planning or policy inference
such that I end up deciding what to do
about this by determining what to do and
then actually carrying out the action
well now my body is acting in the
environment I am effectively kind of
putting my
my the the the outcome of my my
inferential processes into the reality
around me so now that becomes its own
blanket state right is the action of me
picking up you know a piece of food to
eat it I mean that's happening outside
of me right um and and so that's that's
another thing that separates me yet
vicariously connects me with the
environment around me such as the piece
of food um so that that's one way of of
of kind of phrasing what a Markov
blanket is and it's incredibly important
when looking at at modeling because we
we frequently think about as we'll see
later in chapter six um whenever we want
to start creating our own model and and
and simulating things or simulation we
have to very carefully specify what are
these apparent internal States um whe
whether we know their values at first or
not we have to identify what they are
what is it we're trying to model and
then what is not and then what is it
that connects them right so that's
that's a sense of the the Markov blanket
in a nutshell furthermore it kind of
gets it something really important that
we see whenever they start to illustrate
some examples of this which is we've
seen before uh the notion that uh an
agent especially in Chapter 2 might
start to synchronize in some way with
its environment um which can lead some
people astray and thinking that the
generative model necessarily needs to
somehow equate to the environment around
it as if the internal States need to be
perfectly identical to the external
States um but I'll refer back to the
kind of earlier quote an important
precondition for any adaptive system is
that it must enjoy some separation and
autonomy from the environment without
which it would simply dissipate dissolve
and thereby succumb to environmental
Dynamics without meaning to sound too
crude or or strange here I mean the
environment around me doesn't care so
much about my caloric nutrition and and
you know none taken emotionally that's
just how things work I'm the one who
cares about that or in another sense
it's my my body and the the physics and
Physiology beneath it that cares about
that if I gave in to the environmental
Dynamics where my caloric nutrition
simply runs out I will certainly succumb
to the environment around me in some
ways here I have to actively act against
a natural tendency for my body to run
out of caloric nutrition uh you know and
as its gluc close levels start to
deplete um so I have to do things in
order to sort of resist that entropy and
we see some of that kind of more um
physics based language in in this
chapter as well and thinking about it
and thinking about hamiltonian uh
physics and principle of least action so
with figure 3.2 two and I'll I'll kind
of maybe start to open things up not too
long after this but the idea of figure
3.2 here is that we can see if we recall
that X um for example could represent
the the so-called true states of the
environment so X is the the states of
the environment and then we have mu over
here which might the be the internal
states of say a an agent or organism
then we can also have the relationship
between those things or the joint
relationship or distribution um between
those things and the blanket states that
through through which the these two
different kinds of states the the
internal and external are are
vicariously related and so if we see for
this blanket uh X that the environment
actually has a positive correlation but
mu actually has a negative correlation
with that blanket and yet we do see a
kind of
synchrony uh here an inverse synchrony a
negative correlation between uh this is
supposed to be yeah it's labeled uh X
and mu right so this despite the fact
that we can kind of statistically
separate X and mu they still have a
rather you know generally I mean of
course we' want to you know we could
compute the P value or otherwise and and
and or or look at a Pearson's
coefficient or however you would like
but essentially we can we can generally
make out that there's a a negative
correlation here so you know it's my
body runs out
of caloric nutrition that is a natural
thing that happens in the environmental
Dynamics in which I find myself um and
yet um I have a tendency to act against
this by bringing my Hunger down by
eating and so we see that there is this
kind of negative correlation between you
know me losing caloric Nutri losing my
energy and at the same time trying to
fight against it right it's just to bear
in mind again an example showing that
there is no necessity that our internal
States and I I keep phrasing it that way
but there's no necess necessity that any
thing or agent or organism has internal
states that necessarily are one to one
equivalent to
environmental uh external States and in
fact given my examples here that might
actually be very dangerous if they were
fully aligned such as me no longer
eating food in order to you know get
kind of give into the environment around
me um so we we beyond that we're looking
at at things like posterior beliefs like
so how do we fight against this this
natural tendency towards entropy or or
more clearly interpretable definable
like causal relationships we see such as
you know the relationship between hunger
and consumption um we the idea is that
we engage in free energy minimization
that is for those who are familiar with
you know machine learning deep learning
or otherwise we can view free energy
minimization in part as a kind of
optimization problem uh where we are
essentially Trying to minimize
a uh upper bound on surprisal surprisal
in this case for an organism like me you
know again this kind of semi- silly
example of me eating food like um you
know I need x amount of calories per day
right if if I eat too much above or
below that I start to kind of fall
outside of a generally uh a healthy uh
caloric intake level or range of of
caloric intake uh you know with with
obviously very different consequences if
I eat too much versus too little um but
nonetheless it there's some kind of
homeostatic range here that can be
defined so it's kind of that homeostatic
range that in one sense defines me as a
thing in a physical environment and how
I persist which is if I can maintain
these various you know potentially very
very many depending on how granular we
want to be um you know there could be
very many um U preferred States or
homeostats that I need to maintain it
could be blood oxygen flow it could be
caloric nutrition it could be simply you
know my ability to engage in the world
around me in order to uh maintain an
income uh in a market economy in order
to you know get the means for my
survival in the first place um and so we
have that and then we have surprise
meaning it's almost like the the inverse
it'd be like dispreferred States we
don't want surprise right I don't want
my caloric in intake to be too low um
and I don't want it to be too high I
especially don't want it to be too low
um from there what what this does
whenever we look at this in like a
basian framework is that this opens up
the idea of we have expectations and
leaves and so I might a way we could
phrase this is my body expects to
realize its preferences or its
homeostatic ranges uh in practice and so
there's a kind of belief or expectation
that I will remain within my preferred
homeostatic ranges um in this sense uh
we are self- evidencing organisms would
be self- evidencing because the idea is
this is a beliefs based framework we can
phrase it that way they in fact believe
to be uh you know with a very high
probability within their respective
homeostatic ranges um this of course can
lead to a variety of interesting kind of
Dynamics um whether you're familiar with
machine learning or not uh you you can
you know many people can int it the idea
of optimism bias or the idea that
someone might have such a strong belief
in in something in particular
that they will bring it about or they
will just assume it is true and they
might even be opposed to uh
disconfirming evidence you know evidence
to the contrary of what they believe um
another notion that relates to this is
uh the phrasing uh hyper precise priors
which is very relevant here in a basian
context as we already know that priors
or the kinds of beliefs that you bring
to a situation whether they be beliefs
about
um in states of the world but also
actually have beliefs about prior about
observations themselves which are
usually used as the kind of homeostatic
ranges for example I expect to not see
my stomach growling um if it's the case
that it's not growling then that can
also ensure that I'm not hungry or
another way of phrasing it is to not be
hungry is to not see my stomach growling
and if I prefer not to see my stomach
stomach growling and that's a that's a
kind of sign that all is well
right meanwhile with Hyper precise
priors that would be the idea that you
have some kind of um quote unquote
excessive excessively strong prior
beliefs about something that uh might be
might be so terribly strong and and so
terribly kind of precise or certain that
it is very difficult to um start to
disbelieve or unlearn
uh uh uh particularly what might be
harmful beliefs right so this can be
used in the study of say computational
Psychiatry or pathological Behavior Uh
including looking at something like
delusional uh thinking uh in let's say
schizophrenia where one way we could
phrase it is there are such strong priar
about uh what is occurring essentially
in one's own mind that they kind of
overtake one's perception of the reality
around them which results in this kind
of very intensive hallucinatory behavior
when of course the hallucinations are
being produced by what we might phrase
as the the priors of the mind um of
course none of this at all is assuming
that the person is intentionally trying
to make any of this happen or
intentionally choosing to believe in
this way it's not necessarily a soft
belief um in the sense of you know oh I
I choose this out of free will it might
be that you know it's a belief spased
framework it might be that genuinely
computationally neuronally or otherwise
uh there there's something like priors
that are just excessively strong that
lead to the kind of collective neuronal
outcome that is production of
hallucinations so in any case what do we
do we we we self-evidence that is we we
seek out information that actually
reconfirms our beliefs or our
expectations about ourselves and the
world around us um this you know for
those who are interested in in kind of
you know social science or or other
fields like that that would also imply
that you know actually a lot of these
concerns about about um you know opinion
polarization or Tendencies for people to
form in groups and outgroups in order to
just maintain their own respective
social bubbles um and opinion
that that are very polarized between
themselves versus relative to other
groups
um there is you know a lot of kind of
theoretical and and empirical support
for those kinds of Dynamics and and we
very much find them in in active
inference um in in fact a really nice um
paper in the past that I've always found
very interesting was uh this one where
they actually built a full active
inference simulation uh epistemic
communities under active inference
with some recognizable uh researchers
such as Conor Hines Maxwell
ramet barison and so they they construct
a model that essentially looks at
confirmation bias
Conformity um ties together a lot of
otherwise what might be potentially
loose threads in uh psychology a as is
you know what has been viewed as
predominantly a theoretical field uh
rather than necessarily like strictly a
quote unquote hard science and yet this
um the kind of modeling involved here
and Reliance upon you know physical and
and neuroscientific principles does
allow us to start to actually formalize
maybe this is not the best image to
start with just because of the
complexity uh but um to start to
formalize you know these kinds of
Dynamics in interesting ways where they
actually model a very large multi-agent
simulation and then see that yes like
the agents unfortunately whenever
confronted with two distinct opposing
beliefs like based upon the way they
share their information and influence
one another within the broader
environment around them of which all
other agents around them are part of the
environment with which they interact
receive observations commit actions such
as sharing
information um they do start to form
these polarizing groups so um per usual
with modeling there are many other ways
you could potentially approach that kind
of question um this is just this was one
of the the stronger uh papers that I've
seen published and it's you know it's a
rich field just as much as anything else
um and
so I I certainly went past what I
intended to um but we can really quickly
just give figure 3.3 a look um what this
is and I'll try to do it quickly is to
say um from left to right the left image
is uh wi within you know we're modeling
a two-dimensional random dynamical
system with a non-equilibrium steady
state what is that mean it means that we
can have Dynamics such as noise um
stochasticity it means with
non-equilibrium that means that if there
were some kind of steady state to be at
that steady state is not entirely steady
it can shift right um I mean my steady
state at 2 am is to be asleep uh it is
certainly not the case at 2 pm uh to be
asleep and so that's one kind of crude
way of saying that and then so with the
left image this is where we have a
system that actually does have a kind of
surprise minimization Dynamic about it
um they don't actually Define the
specific rule it's following nor any of
the variables the point is just to show
that it tends towards uh starting from
coordinates
55 it eventually tends towards over time
this General Central area and doesn't
quite leave there it doesn't necessarily
have to stop at a particular point but
it it stays generally around there and
then the image to the far right we'll
skip the middle one for a moment this is
simply a kind of kind of gradient spread
um or way of looking at what are the
most surprising states that EX exist in
this nine equilibrium uh steady state
random dynamical system and so they say
that this Center Circle is where states
are least surprising you can kind of
view this as there is an organism who's
adapting and trying to learn how to live
in this uh non-equilibrium steady state
environment just like I have to figure
out how to navigate the Dynamics of my
body's need for sleep in ways that work
well with say a kind of uh you know
circadian clock where going to sleep
roughly around the same time and getting
up roughly around the same time every
day uh tends to be most helpful uh both
in practice and and and and in study so
um we could view it as that right uh it
the view this as a kind of mirror the
agent is kind of staying eventually
arrives at and stays within this least
surprising uh area of the the state
space
meanwhile the
middle uh diagram is just to show we
could have something that doesn't
attempt to minimize surprise right it
also starts at coordinate
55 but then it follows an incredibly
kind of flu
fluctuating uh you know irregular not
very well patterned whatsoever path uh
as it kind of succumbs to the the kind
of stochastic
uh you know dissipative uh entropic
forces of the uh non-equil
non-equilibrium steud State environment
in which it exists and it because it's
not you know there's no kind of control
here uh we could phrase that in the
reinforcement learning sense for anyone
familiar with that or simply the idea of
you know a person who chooses to act
against dis against entropy or not it's
kind of like the left side is an example
of uh uh an organiz
striving to Exist by minimizing its
surprise in order to instead stay in
preferred non surprise inducing States
uh as opposed to the middle graph where
we end up with an agent who fully
succumbs to to environmental Dynamics
without any way of kind of putting up a
a fight against them as it were we get
many interesting relationships here as
they uh the authors start to further tie
together their work with with physics
with information Theory and so on so we
actually see that um the maximization of
log probability of
observations which is kind of just like
saying um that we are trying to
self-evidence we're seeking out
observations that we want to see such as
I want to not see my stomach growl I
want to see my stomach silent and we
could View that as in a sense being
equivalent to the minimization of
Shannon entropy for anyone familiar with
Claud Shannon and his kind of
representation of entropy in information
Theory um but the the point is you know
it's kind of kind of how spread out or
uniform or
uncertain is you know the the the the
probability of the various kinds of
evidence that we're finding we want to
be able to find more certain evidence
that makes us more certain cluding about
our beliefs which in turn from The High
Road of active inference would be very
important for maintaining our survival
I've certainly spoken for some time so
I'm just curious if there's anyone who
has any questions or or is curious about
anything that they might want to
discuss yeah so I I understand why you
would model homeostasis as associ ating
the preferred state with priors I I also
see that there's evidence that very
strong priors look like preferences in
the world very often but going in the
other direction is something I have
problem with this idea so so going from
very strong priors to preferences I
think you can justify but going from but
saying whenever there's a preference
it's a very strong prior that that
doesn't seem like it could possibly be
adaptive because
uh there there
are
uh you know there there are
times when it's important
to expect something that you don't want
if you know it's typical for for
example I think we talked about this
John with the lion and the child a
little
bit so it is a really important question
but the the kind of first principle here
is it's a framework for expressing what
you just said so you can go anywhere in
the face space with this and that one
precise and this and that one labile and
this person's perspective on that one as
that it just it's like in the generic
case of generic homeostasis generalized
homeostasis all that it's just
expressivity and then how it is for any
given thing capital t that is an
empirical question or it's it's
empirically
analytical like just here's the
properties of this map within this
framework coordinate
system so you know it's a valid concern
but it's like there's no particular life
or death situation of any
organism that is like necessarily like
or the high road is at is at
risk so would you say there are
preferences that don't come from very
strong priors that maybe all very strong
priors act like preferences but maybe
not all preferences come from very
strong priors is that is that a an
answer so just just in terms of
coherence with the uh the sort of
ontology or the the terminology that's
used in the textbook um so preferences
here or we're looking at preferred
States um they themselves could
considered themselves to be to be priors
um they're they're all kind of
equivalent it depends on how you want to
look at things and especially depends on
how you want to model things so it's
something that's very commonly done uh
and I I kind of I don't know how well I
described it earlier but um frequently
we take priors over observations it's
not always the case people can you know
do this differently but it's very often
the case that they they model prior
specifically over observation rather
than states to be representative of
preferences um not even then not
necessarily all cases um but and it
maybe it would be best for me to jump to
um a figure that could help kind of
elucidate this a little bit better um a
good example is the
pp model um which will get to shortly
but the the the
point here we are
so this is the P PDP I think this
features in chapter 7 um it and so here
we're looking at this one this one
parameter amidst everything else going
on here um but C is is used to refer to
uh priors over pre priors over
observations AKA preferences and you you
see that it's related to calculating G
which is used to score policies what
does that mean that means that you're
able to score uh your potential actions
available to you or or you're able to
plan uh actions accordingly and engage
in policy inference using uh these kind
of expectations you have about what you
are going to see which in terms of the
letter c the parameter C is just a
probability distribution priors over
observations that stay fixed because
they stay fix fixed which you can
imagine like just like you know I need
roughly 2,000 calories a day that's
generally fixed whether I want to change
my mind about that or not I will
probably have a bad time if I try to
change my mind about that because it
will not align with you know what I
repeatedly observe which is that you
know I actually asked about that too for
for exactly this reason so is maybe the
resolution to the lion thing that the
child starts with preferences he won't
see any lion or starts with prior that
he won't see any lions and then uh that
initial prior is maintained as the
preference even though the
epistemological prior updates through
basy and
inference yeah that could be like a
locked in state like I know there's a
pro a project with PTSD Andre can share
more but just those are the Dynamics big
picture zooming out from this one
specific issue about preference and
prior and where's precise and whereas it
isn't which system are we talking about
the textbook is just saying here's the
expressivity including like nested
systems systems with body and mind
elements so it's like you got the
grammar there you're asking the right
formatting of question and you can
actually just build maps of that to
model different
territories but that that's not on the
high road that's the empirical
half whereas this is more like your
questions and thinking about thing
Concepts yeah I'm just asking about this
it's a chapter three and it's a number
of chapters and it it's a bit weird like
the pragmatic value thing it's
associated with like I don't know if I I
would say that pragmatic value is always
you know a logarithm of probabilities it
seems that that could work sometimes but
maybe not all the
time yeah it's I mean
that's and that is exactly where
preferences are are implicated but it's
just I mean another way of viewing this
idea of preferences and and I keep
relating them to homeostasis and they
even at one point in this chapter say
that that preferences in a sense are
like defining the phenotype of of an
organism yeah well homostasis is is an
example where this definitely work it's
just yeah issues of having to predict
the environment
uh could could run you into trouble
because uh if you if you act like you'll
get what you want you you can get into
trouble yeah I I I often whenever I I I
use this uh you know caloric intake my
stomach is growling therefore I'm hungry
I use that example a lot just because
it's so intuitive for literally everyone
but I always I I sometimes extend it and
say like well we're still in a partially
observable environment what I mean is is
my stomach growling a sign of hunger or
is it a sign of like a throbbing stomach
ulcer um the the you know the state I
should you know
infer you know if I'm not sure about one
of those things or if I'm very sure that
it's a sign of hunger when in fact it's
a sign of a deeper problem I'm going to
get very far like you know LED astray uh
similarly with I I'm not totally
familiar with this child and lion
example that you all have given I'm
guessing it's maybe a child who
confronts uh you know a lion and his
it's the point that the the child can't
afford uh for the for his preferences
about seeing a line to be similar to the
to the actual probability belief because
the the child has to not want to see the
line and the child has to have an
accurate probability of of the of
running into
it so so I mean we could even depends on
how granular you want to go and and and
Daniel did make the point about you know
we end up making a lot of sort of
modeling decisions even even in these
kind of natural language examples that
we give I mean another way you could you
could drill into that even further and
say even before the child makes any kind
of like explicit knowing uh executive
functioning uh kind of related uh
inference about a lion um you could even
you could even step further to the the
fastest time scale which is like it
might be that the child sees the line
there's some kind of connection made
there and suddenly the child uh you know
starts to experience light amounts of
perspiration a heightened heart rate um
all kinds of other signs of kind of
physiological arousal that you know
might lead one to infer that you know
this child is now suddenly afraid yeah
right and their stress system and
cortisol and all of that have been
activated U pretty rapidly so it's not
just that we don't want to see a lion
but like another way of viewing it as I
don't want to see my body going go into
that state um th this relates
to uh uh kind of like a lot of work
that's been done in affective
Neuroscience so looking at like you know
uh the idea of emotions actually being
inferences from the physiological
experiences we we have um you know it's
kind of like oh I'm angry I know I'm
angry because I see that my you know my
fist is shaking and I have a certain
expression on my face you know almost
unintentionally like a reaction so you
can even relate you know phys the one's
you know autonomic like fastpaced
reactions as observations themselves
that you don't want to see or do want to
see um yeah I I hopefully I didn't like
over complicate that or or make it more
confusing but I hope that was useful in
some kind of way um
but it is a good it is a good question
um another way of viewing preferences or
or these kinds of expectations is you
know later chapters again we look at
like attracting points um the idea of
you know these are kind of like
attractors we we're already introduced
to it here because we see
in allor right figure yeah that we spent
some time with already like this
leftmost area
this is like you know following a system
and and moving towards
preferred States or moving towards like
this this kind of preferred region um as
opposed to not having that with so so so
it's kind of like on the left it's like
with these kinds of surprise
minimization Dynamics involved there's a
tendency to move a certain way um as
opposed to in the Middle where you know
there's no attractor here there's
there's no this is pure kind of FL
depending on maybe your initial starting
point and then whatever plays out from
there in you know your error terms and
you know whatever else is involved but
there's nothing pulling you towards you
know say some low surprisal region of a
state space um you know it' be like
again me not eating food and slowly
succumbing to the you know the physical
processes around me um and another
interesting thing for those interested
in computational modeling is also uh
related which is how what happens you
know we just looked at that middle graph
of like you know the the the agent who's
kind of spiraling out of nowhere there's
no attractor um they did
another experiment when I say they this
experiment goes pretty far back or at
least not in 2022 when this textbook was
published
um but uh they it's this um there's this
phenomena um oh 1985 uh phenomena of the
inhibition of return which is pretty
interesting so um John you previously
brought up the idea of pragmatic value
and we know from uh previously I I don't
want this equation to mislead us maybe
I'll jump back um because this one has
to do with
with using different kinds of terms
including novelty um which also is a
fair breakdown of expected free energy
but still I just want to stick to um
differentiating epistemic
from equations of course um
differentiating
epistemic value AKA Information Gain
with pragmatic value which as you saw
whenever this little icon guy isn't
there here we go um see the preferences
are implicating the pragmatic value it's
kind of like you know um I could eat
food or I could spend some time looking
up restaurants of where I could get food
um yeah if I spent time looking up
restaurants maybe I'll end up learning
something interesting uh and but it's
the actual Act of like attaining and
eating the food that that kind of
bestows the direct pragmatic value of
realizing my preferences here in the
sense of not wanting to see my my
stomach Rowling living along those lines
um so it's only in C that this plays out
right so that kind of means information
game Information Gain in one sense okay
so this the one problem I'm having is I
don't really understand what C is okay
sure so um one way we could look at C is
this same chapter here with the
PDP
um here we are so I don't mean to skip
ahead so much and I don't want to
overwhelm but you can see
here that this is for the
tze problem I believe yeah um this is
the tze problem and let's just ignore
the these are two different
submatrices within the big
C sub uh full Matrix
containing preferences prior over
observations so in the tze the the mouse
can receive it has two different
observation modalities we're not going
to over complicate we're just going to
focus on one of them it's the second one
here what does this second one represent
well we have essentially a single Vector
right so
it's a vector is you know like a like a
one column or one row um transposed
Matrix so the first inry is zero which
based on the problem I'll just tell you
what it is it is um this is to not see
um a
reward or nor a shock the here's the t-
maze the t- maze is you can uh the mouse
can essentially it can go uh to multiple
spaces within this little t-shaped maze
it can go left uh or it go right meaning
it can go take a left wing or right wing
based on its starting position and kind
of closer to the center down uh area and
and the idea is on the left will be
either a piece of cheese like a reward
um and on the other side will be a
negative stimulus such as like a little
shock or something along those lines but
you can you can already make out the the
abstract notion that is you know this is
an opportunity to achieve pragmatic
value uh by going for you know cheese
and IDE ideally the the the mouse wants
to to find the cheese and so it's going
to have to engage in state inference
about trying to figure out which the
left or right arm of the teamas like
which location uh the the the C1 relates
to locations and observing the locations
it's at um C2 is it this this first
entry is where um there's nothing
meaning no cheese but also no negative
stimulus it has a preference of zero and
we're just just with me about what these
numbers mean they're a little arbitrary
but they they mean something um this
middle value six is saying that with
with kind of a power of or or number of
six the the mouse prefers the cheese
right the the reward um this the second
entry represents the the probability for
the reward um and then the third one
negative -6 obviously very bad this is
you can already see here this is their
preference for the aversive stim with it
being negative negative being less than
zero you you can see it's almost like a
ranking system here of the the mouse
strongly dis prefers the aversive
stimulus um it is pretty indifferent
neutral to the absence of either the
reward or the negative stimulus and then
it strongly prefers the observation of
the cheese right what the reason why
this doesn't look like a probability
distribution is simply that we you know
you could Define it as a probability
distribution and that is ultimately what
it is um sometimes people in active
inference they do it this way just to
make it more
intuitive um but in any case you run it
through the softmax function right and
whenever you do that that is what kind
of converts it into a probability
distribution but then furthermore it
kind of
amplifies um the the resulting
probability distribution so what what's
going to happen is you know it
it just look at how it's for practically
this formulation means the attractive
stimulus is considered e to six or 400
times more probable than the neutral
stimulus under the rat's generative
model so kind of just you the softmax
comes up often it also comes up in
Precision modulation um but um sorry I
just realized uh Daniel your hand was up
yeah I just wanted to add one point on
that the the soft Max point so that sums
an
arbitrary set of numbers to one so it's
like this and and this is the kind of
stuff that gets learned in stats classes
like if you don't sum it to one or frame
it in terms of a distribution you're
dealing with a scenario where like even
on the next time step there's either
less than something happening or more
than something happening like you C you
can't sum up the events that could
happen for a given variable it's like
that has to sum to one to reflect the
Total distribution of what could happen
for that to persist so it's like to go
off of that kind of summing to one
statistical
approach um it it's
like it puts you outside of the
empirical because you want to have a
framework where you can observe it and
model it statistically otherwise it's
kind of like saying like there's some
other way to model noisy processes or
processes with partial information that
doesn't fall under sta statistical
approach wait so to maintain the sum of
one is there some kind of unitary
Evolution yeah like in the quantum
setting that is called the unitary and
at a deeper level but just at a more
practical level the softmax takes this
string like 066 or 011 or 1 z0
or2 and it proportional lies it and you
can adjust the the posterior
proportioning like the pie chart that is
the soft Max output of these numbers
like that's 100%
tunable the question which numbers to
use so after you do the soft backs you
still have a vector it's just that all
of these sum to one and the the higher
values are Amplified yeah like just
statistical distributions overall like
gaussian with a mean and a variance it's
it's two numbers but because you know
that it's going to get plugged into a
gaussian you know that it's going to sum
to one under the
curve can this change over time these
numbers yes preferences can be updated
any preference in a given model any any
variable could be fixed or learnable
okay so yeah so you you you you yeah
that that'll give you unitary Evolution
so if you evolve it with a matrix that
Matrix will have to be unitary so yeah
it's kind of like y equals 4 like it's a
function that on one hand it does it
does have time as a dimension it could
but it just stays at four so it's like
whether you choose a fixed parameter or
you choose like kind of like a colan
filter like a distribution unfolding
through time with it just you're within
the statistics dummy that's what
parameter updating and learning is
about using statistical methods so it's
like again if you have some other
method this is the what this is what the
current statistical
packages are implementable it's not that
there aren't methods outside of doing
probabilistic statistics
and there's yeah yeah it I mean with
with the examples that we see often in
like kind of the textbook
oriented um examples that are given the
teamm ETC um the preferences are not
learned but you know seconding Daniel
they absolutely could be learned which
is part of why I brought up like this
paper here among you know probably a
dozen others at this point but yeah any
parameter any of these you know
probability distribution within your
agent can be learned and it can be
learned via free energy minimization
essentially right um it's only policy
inference that that uses expected free
energy so um yeah everything else is
kind of
updatable the the thing is it's kind of
tough because you know with the idea of
homeostasis or having preferred States
it's like you would assume that those
wouldn't really change too much um we
can think of many instances where they
would change I mean you can think of
you know a child at a very young age
requires a significantly lower caloric
intake than like you know a 20 or
30-year-old adult and then even further
once they're at an older age the the
required caloric intake starts to go
down again so I mean that that's one way
of viewing it it's like is there
preference learning is there just
genuine you know changes within the
organism such that what defines its
homeostasis itself changes over time um
there are different ways you can look at
so so that's like a soft natural
language explanation that refers to
physiology meanwhile you can also just
look at it as purely like you know
statistics and machine learning or do
you want this model to be learned or
learnable or not um do you want to
parameterize it in a particular way you
know what it what is you know anything
related to things like like learning
rates or or precisions or uh modulation
or otherwise all those things could
apply um it's really just what do you
want to model what do you want to create
and what actually makes sense and then
you know ideally if possible depending
on your phenomena of interest you could
engage from there and like empirical
testing and and fitting of the model to
empirical data if you're in that kind of
domain that you know that that something
like that would make sense you know um I
mean similarly you could the you know so
so so D meanwhile you notice how similar
these look to see except they don't do
the soft Max instead they're just at the
start they're making it clear that this
is going to sum to one this sums to one
they I don't know entirely why they do
that I don't think it makes it that much
more intuitive to understand but uh to
to multiply this by one half but you can
imagine this is 0. 5.5 like this is a
5050 prior over hidden States whereas C
was a prior over the observations such
as is there cheese here is there a
negative stimuli here is there nothing
uh you know absence of those things here
um here it's like you know D is let's
see D2 two contexts oh is the cheese on
the left or is it on the right you know
starting with a prior of which is
essentially after we multiply uh you
know 50/50 it's 0.5 versus 0.5 something
to one know so um yeah and then I guess
just well we're about out of time I just
I really like this uh this inhibition of
return concept it's simply if you if you
recall with with expected free energy
minimization we have Information Gain
and pragmatic value you can imagine if C
was highly uniform you know like uh you
let's say the the the mouse equally
prefers um nothing as it prefers like
imagine all three of these ignore the
soft magx or you could still leave it
there either way let's imagine these
were 33.33 .33 you know essentially
summing to one uh and and so there's an
equivalent preference for everything
right meaning no it's a fully uniform
distribution you could plot out the pmf
just you know everything's at the same
level um and what would happen is your
expected free energy term it'd be very
difficult right to to rank available
actions to take should I go left should
I go right should I stop for a second
think about it I'm not sure because I
don't know how to weigh any of these in
terms of pragmatic value because I don't
know how to derive PR pragmatic value
because I don't prefer any one
particular thing versus another it's all
equivalent well then what happens in
that kind of strange hypothetical case
you're only relying on Information Gain
whenever it comes to action selection
and policy inference so what does that
mean that means that all of your actions
since since there's no reward you know
nothing is can be defined as reward you
don't prefer anything more than anything
else so instead all of your behavior is
essentially based on sorry I'm scrolling
around so much I just um but uh all of
your behavior will be centered on
Information Gain in which case they they
did this um let's see Yep this
experiment where they just have an agent
navigate like a a a maze or is it even a
maze is it just a grid um like there's
nothing to be you know solved there's no
maze to be conquered or won because you
did the correct thing because you don't
you don't care essentially you don't
care because your your your beliefs are
are uniform um and so they just the
whole point is this agent who has no
ability to to figure out some kind of
like you know Tipping Point for
pragmatic value because they prefer
everything equally they end up just
moving around the maze but in
interestingly they don't stay why don't
they stay put they don't because there's
no information gain from staying put
right so it's just kind of to show like
there there's this kind of balancing
actor I don't even know if that's the
right way to phrase it but we have
Information Gain have pragmatic value
these are the two main things that kind
of Define behavior it's like how do I
choose what to do well will I get new
information by choosing an action or
will I get pragmatic value out of
choosing an action or will I get both
you know there's no they're not not
necessarily two contending or fighting
uh values right it's simply that you can
compute both because we you know
essentially have the sort of equations
for that where of course we have X you
know our states our observations and our
actions the three essential components
of model as well as C and then again the
degree of uniformity of C can very much
um impact the behavior of the agent
anyway I recognize we've gone over on
time um but um
interesting conversation thank you for
your questions John appreciate it I'm
sure they they'll be useful to to other
people who uh watch that this if not now
then in future on a on the recording so
um thank you everyone and then next week
um at this same time it'll be back to
cohort 7 and we'll be looking at chapter
nine uh of the textbook that looks at
you
know data analysis essentially and model
analysis and and just like you know
group comparisons and a lot of kind of
interesting things that happen after you
have defined your model and your
environments and you kind of start
playing things out uh and then that
morning we'll we'll have cohort 8 I I
think we continuing with the same
chapter if I'm not mistaken so um thank
you all so much and uh have a great
evening or whatever time it is for you
now so have a good one thank
you bye